Guide to the American College for Girls records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series VI: Records of the Office of the Trustees, New York
  The New York Office of the Near East College Association served as the link between the college and its supporters in the United States. For many years, beginning in the 1920s, the office was headed by Albert Staub. These records are comprised of the two major sub-series: one the correspondence with ACG's President, Kathryn Adams, and the other, the correspondence with Dean Eleanor Burns.
  ACG's inadequate endowment meant that fundraising continued to be a major concern for Adams and this is reflected in the records. The Near East College Association raised money but it was apportioned among several colleges.
  In 1924, ACG organized a Social Service Center and Adams reports on the significance of its work. The assistance the center provided to village residents was important as outreach for the college as well as providing useful experience for those students interested in social work as a career.
  In 1928, Adams reported that Mrs. Charles A. Lindbergh, mother of the famous pilot, had joined the faculty as a visiting Professor of Chemistry, while Alice Morrow, sister of Dwight Morrow, U.S. Ambassador to Mexico, agreed to act as hostess for visiting dignitaries. It was hoped and expected that Mrs. Lindbergh would afterward use her influence on behalf of the college. Unfortunately, she was not happy there and Adams later wrote that "a tremendous load has been taken from me," when Mrs. Lindbergh left (January 14, 1929). Miss Morrow, on the other hand, remained and was supportive of the college. Adams's letters are informative. She reports on activities of the alumnae and on the visits of dignitaries to Istanbul.
  There is a folder of correspondence from Dr. Marion Talbot, who served as acting president of ACG during 1931 and 1932. Her letters discuss the difficulties the college was experiencing, due in part to the impact of the worldwide economic crisis. In addition, there are several folders of correspondence from Dr. Virginia Gildersleeve, dean of Barnard College, who served as a trustee of ACG for many years.
  The correspondence of Burns reflects her responsibilities for recruitment of faculty as well as the procurement and awarding of scholarships. Moreover, she discusses in detail specific problems that arose between the college and the Turkish Minister of Education. Many of her letters refer to attached enclosures such as translations of articles from the Turkish press, but these are not filed with the correspondence and may have been lost.
  There is an exchange of correspondence between Staub and Mary Patrick covering the years 1922-23, the last of Patrick's years as president. The next correspondence is dated 1933-1935, which includes the years of Patrick's retirement, but that is hardly an accurate description for she remained active in fundraising and continued a lively interest in the affairs of the college.
  - Correspondence to Staub and Olmstead from Peet, 1926-1942 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Staub/Laurence Moore/Burns, 1924-1926 (Box 28, Folder 2-4)
  - Correspondence Staub/Burns, 1927-1930 (Box 29, Folder 5-9)
  - Correspondence to Talbot from Staub, 1931 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Staub/Burns, 1931-1932 (Box 29, Folder 11-17)
  - Correspondence Staub/Burns, 1933-1948. (Box 30, Folder 18-21)
  - Correspondence Staub/Adams, 1924-1931 (Box 31, Folder 32-46)
  - Correspondence to Staub from Talbot, 1931-1932 (Box 31, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence Staub/Virginia Gildersleeve, 1926-1950 (Box 31, Folder 48-49)
  - Correspondence Hardy/Gildersleeve, 1951-1962 (Box 32, Folder 50-52)
- Series VII: Financial Records, 1899-1946
  While this series essentially covers financial matters, it is in the form of correspondence that includes discussion of the reasons for property acquisition, new buildings, supplies, and other expenditures. It is therefore of interest apart from strictly monetary concerns.
  There are a number of letters from Mary Mills Patrick and William W. Peet that discuss the 1905 fire at the Uskudar campus as well as the move from Uskudar to Arnavutköy. In one letter, dated July 31, 1911, Peet refers to a major event outside the campus. On the anniversary of the proclamation of the Turkish Constitution, July 22, two large fires broke out in Istanbul that destroyed no less than 10,000 houses and rendered 50,000-60,000 homeless. The suspicion exists, Peet reports, "that the fires are the work of incendiaries and that it is one form of reactionary protest against the present government." As a precaution, the college hired a night watchman.
  Mary Patrick reports on developments at the college and also on her fundraising efforts in the United States. After her retirement in 1924, the correspondence in this series tends to deal more exclusively with financial matters. There are some useful summary documents; e.g., the construction costs of each building on the Arnavutkoy campus as of its completion in 1915 (Lucius E. Thayer correspondence to Leolin H. Keeney, June 24,1932, Box 32, Folder 16).
  The records of the 1930s and the World War II era document the financial difficulties involved in operating the college during the Great Depression and the wartime years. Shortly after World War II, there is a report on the college, dated May 10,1947, by President Floyd Black on his return to the campus after a four-month absence in the U.S. (Box 32, Folder 25a).
  Another document worth noting is in the file of Business Manager A. W. Sellar. It is a six-page "History of the Musurus Palace at Arnavutköy", which was built in the early nineteenth century on the site that later became part of the ACG campus. The document is dated August 7,1929 (Box 32, Folder 25c).
  - General correspondence to Day, treasurer, 1899-1906 (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
  - General correspondence to Rutan, treasurer, 1905-1911 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to George Adams, treasurer, from Patrick, 1910-1914 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence to Murray 1914-1919 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Notes for informal report made by Haskell, 1922 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence to Olmstead from Bernetta Miller, bursar, 1926-1929 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to Leolin H. Keeney, treasurer, from Adams, 1926 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence between Keeney and Miller, 1927-1930 (Box 32, Folder 12-15)
  - General correspondence to Keeney, 1932-l939 (Box 32, Folder 16-19)
  - Correspondence to Harlan Conn, bursar, from Staub, 1925 (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - General correspondence to Staub re financial matters, 1927-1939 (Box 32, Folder 21-25)
  - Correspondence to Staub from Burns and Floyd Black, 1940-1946 (Box 32, Folder 25a)
  - Correspondence to Staub from A.W. Sellar, business manager, 1928 (Box 32, Folder 25b)
  - Correspondence to Adams from Sellar, 1929 (Box 32, Folder 25c)
  - General correspondence to Elbert C. Stevens, business manager-grounds and buildings, 1930-1933 (Box 32, Folder 26)
  - General correspondence re finances American Service Funds, 1934-1935 (Box 32, Folder 27)
  - General correspondence re salaries in depression years at ACG and RC, 1932-1936 (Box 32, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence to Staub from Herman Kreider, bursar, 1940-1944 (Box 32, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence to Kreider and Francis Potts, bursar, from Staub, 1940-1943 (Box 32, Folder 30)
- Series VIII: Publicity, Official Events and Historical, General
  This series contains some printed materials--pamphlets and newspaper articles pertaining to ACG and major events in the Near East. News clippings date from the early 1900s to the late 1940s and include portrait photographs with brief biographical data on some faculty members (Box 33, Folders 1-2). There are fundraising pamphlets and brochures dating to 1907 and 1909. Materials relating to official events at the college include a richly detailed scrapbook containing Charter Day speeches, extracts from letters, commencement programs, news clippings and memorabilia covering the period from the 1880s to 1907 (Box 34, Folder 1: This material is fragile).
  There is a 46-page typescript copy of a journal kept by Nettie Dodd from 1866 -1868. Her sister was Isabel Dodd, a longtime faculty member at ACG, her brother, William S. Dodd, was a medical missionary in Turkey.
  Several articles by Mary Mills Patrick and others focus on the work of the college and the education of women. They span the period from 1908 to 1955.
  Finally, there are a number of studies of the college including doctoral dissertations, M.A. theses and historical essays on the general subject of education in Turkey. Most are in typescript. A brief account by Dr. Floyd Black, written in 1944, relates his experiences with ACG while teaching at Robert College, and during the first year of his presidency.
  - Historical/Publicity
    - Photo reprints of faculty and campus, 1920s (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
    - Xerox of a photo collage titled, "Constantinople Woman's College Telescope", 1931 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - "College Magazine" (one issue), 1913 (Box 33, Folder 3a)
    - Newspaper articles (alphabetical by subject), 1917-1922 (Box 33, Folder 4-5)
    - Newspaper articles (miscellaneous), 1906-1954 (Box 33, Folder 6-10)
  - Fundraising: Reports and Brochures
    - Fundraising brochures, 1907-1909 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlets and articles, 1907-1919 (Box 33, Folder 12-13)
    - Brochure titled "Constantinople College", 1917 (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - Brochures, 1914, 1919 (Box 33, Folder 15)
    - Pamphlets with descriptions of ACG, 1916-1921 (Box 33, Folder 16)
    - Brochure, "Constantinople Woman's College/Medical Work", [1920s] (Box 33, Folder 17)
    - Pamphlets published by the Near East College Association, [1930s] (Box 33, Folder 18)
    - "Ten Year Development Fund," a statement concerning the American College for Girls, 1958 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - "The Second Century Development Plan, Progress Report and Future Goals", 1961 (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - Official College Events
    - Commencement address given by James B. Angell, 1898 (Box 33, Folder 21)
    - Commencement descriptions, 1904;1908 (Box 33, Folder 22-23)
    - Document written by Peet for laying of cornerstone ceremony, 1914 (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - Program invitations, 1912-1923 (Box 33, Folder 25-26)
    - 25th commencement program, 1915 (Box 33, Folder 27)
    - Program of commencement exercises for preparatory department, 1924 (Box 33, Folder 28)
    - Commencement programs, 1913-1952 (Box 33, Folder 29)
  - Memoirs, Theses, Articles
    - ACG Scrapbook; clippings, invitations, letters l880s­ca.1907 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - "From Home," xerox of journal written by Nettie Dodd in Turkey, 1866 (Box 34, Folder 1a)
    - "Constantinople Home," reprint of article by Caroline Borden, 1890 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - "Women of the Orient," paper prepared by Borden, 1911 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - "Echoes of the New Ottoman Constitution," booklet written by ACG students, 1908 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - "The Emancipation of Mohammeden Women," by Patrick (reprint from The National Geographic Magazine ), 1909 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - "Constantinople College Under the Present War Conditions," by Patrick (reprint from The New York Evening Post ), 1915 (Box 34, Folder 5a)
    - "Asia Minor in the Time of the Seven Wise Men," by Patrick (reprint from The National Geographic Magazine ), 1920 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - "An Oasis of Peace," reprint of an article written by Patrick, 1920s (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Articles relating to archaeological findings in Turkey written by Professor A.H. Sayce, 1910 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - "American Education for Girls in Turkey," reprint of article by Alice Lawton, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - "Constantinople College, The American College for Girls at Constantinople," by Eveline A. Thomson (reprint of article from the Journal of the Association of College Alumnae ), 1916 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - "Glimpses of Bulgaria during the Present Crisis," article by Mary M. Haskell, 1918 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Address to the Forum," by Dean Louise B. Wallace (reprint from the Mount Holyoke Alumnae Quarterly ), 1919 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - "Constantinople College for Women and Homemaking Education," typescript by Eda Lord Demarest, 1927 (Box 34, Folder F13)
    - "Constantinople College," typescript, author unknown, 1900s (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - "College on the Bosphorus," by Virginia Voss reprint from Mademoiselle magazine, 1900s (Box 34, Folder 14a)
    - "Flap-Jack Alley in Constantinople," typescript by Eda Lord Murphy, [undated] (Box 34, Folder 15)
    - List of books catalogued at the Anne Taylor Case Library (ACG), 1920s (Box 34, Folder 16)
  - Manuscripts/Typescripts
    - "The American College for Girls," 2l-page typescript of ACG's history written by Floyd Black, 1950s (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - "Social Sciences in Turkish Elementary Education," written by Behidje Sadik, class of 1931 (78-page manuscript published by the Trustees), 1931 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - "Development of the American College for Girls at Istanbul in Turkey During Twenty-Five Years of the Turkish Republic," M.A. Thesis by Marjorie Leslie McKillop, 1948 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - "Turkey for the Turks," paper written by Grace Kellogg, 1952 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - 10-page outline for a history of ACG by Ruth Bradley, 1968 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified manuscript of RC/ACG history, with appendix of "firsts" (alumni/ae achievements), 1970s (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - History of RC/ACG, ms. Fincancl, 1970s (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - "Mary Mills Patrick and The American College for Girls at Istanbul in Turkey," ms. of published dissertation by Ethel Nichols Thomas, 1979 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Caroline Borden typed manuscript: “The American College for Girls at Constantinople in Turkey. 1871-1921” (Box 36)
- Series IX: Minutes
  - November 1894-December 1904 (Box 37, Volume 1)
  - February 1905-February 1908 (Box 37, Volume 2)
  - April 1908-December 1916 (Box 37, Volume 3)
  - April 1919-December 1920 (Box 37, Volume 4)
  - University Ledger, 1924-1930 (Box 37, Volume 5)
  - January 1921-December 1925 (Box 38, Volume 6)
  - May 1926-November 1929 (Box 38, Volume 7)
  - May 1930-Sept. 1947 (Box 38, Volume 8)
  - November 1947-May 1955 (Box 38, Volume 9)
  - January 1949-January 1956 (Box 38, Volume 10)
  - August 1955-July 1958 (Box 38, Volume 11)
  - September 1958-November 1959 (Box 38, Volume 12)
  - November 1959-May 1960 (Box 38, Volume 13)
- Series X: Photographs
  - Students at Work .Library; students studying Laboratory Classroom General (Box 39)
  - Student, Informal Students, Extracurricular (includes clubs, social service) (Box 40)
  - Students, Groups (pre 1935) (Box 41)
  - Students, Groups (post 1935) (Box 42)
  - Students, Groups (Box 42)
  - Charter Day Celebration (includes Library) (Box 42)
  - Students, Groups (mostly Pageants) (Box 43)
  - Students, Individuals (Box 43)
  - Commencement Photographs (pre 1924 College and Orta, Group and Individual (Box 44)
  - Commencement Photographs (post 1924 College, Group and Individual) (Box 45)
  - Commencement Photographs (Box 46)
  - Sports (Box 47)
  - Child Study Center (Box 47)
  - Ancillary Staff (Box 48)
  - Faculty, Individuals and Groups (Box 49)
  - Administrators (Box 50)
  - Campus (individual buildings, miscellaneous, interior) (Box 51)
  - E.D.H. Clarke Bench (plateau) (Box 51)
  - Campus Buildings Uskudar Campus (Box 52)
  - Campus Buildings (Arnavutkoy Campus, General views, pre 1971) (Box 53)
  - Construction Photographs (pre 1971) (Box 54)
  - Individual Buildings (Gould, Bingham, Barton Halls, pre 1971) (Box 55)
- Series XI: Microfilms
  - Minutes, April 1908-April 1959 (1 reel) (Box 56)
  - Minutes, May 1959 – June 1960 (1 reel) (Box 56)
- Additional I
  - Girls' College-Financial Records (Box 1)
  - Bequests/Scholarships/Gifts/Funds (Box 1)
  - Estates/Wills (Box 1)
  - Deeds/Buildings (Box 1)
  - Court Order/Instructions in case of death (misc.) (Box 1)
  - Collateral material: interesting PR, etc. (Box 1)
  - Hamlin, Cyrus--Letters written by (Box 1)
  - Letter written by Christopher Rhinelander Robert to Hamlin, New York, August 10, 1865 (Box 1)
  - Proposed draft of By-Laws (1899) (Box 2)
  - Revised draft of By-Laws (1907) (Box 2)
  - By-Laws (1908) (Box 2)
  - Charter and By-laws as amended (December 12, 1911) (Box 2)
  - Charter and By-laws as amended (April 1915) (Box 2)
  - Charter and By-laws as amended (Nov 1930) (Box 2)
  - Charter and By-laws as amended (May 1940) (Box 2)
  - By-Laws as amended (July 1956) (Box 2)
  - Documents: Reorganization of ACG as institution independent from Women's Board (Box 2)
  - 1906-1908 (Box 2)
  - By-laws as amended (Oct 26, 1971) (Box 2)
  - By-laws as amended (March 7, 1974) (Box 2)
  - By-laws as amended (May 10, 1985) (Box 2)
  - The American College for Girls Information Bulletin (1961-1962 1962-1963 1965) (Box 2)
  - The American College for Girls at Constantinople President's Report (1891-1903) (Box 2)
  - The American College for Girls at Constantinople Report of the President (1904-1913) (Box 2)
  - The American College for Girls Calendar (1889-1890 - 1910-1912) (Box 2)
  - American College for Girls at Constantinople Calendar (Bulletin) June, 1913 1921-1922) (Box 2)